<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <author>
    <name>Jade Thornton</name>
  </author>
  <title>Jade Thornton: The Blog</title>
  <link href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/feed/jade.atom" rel="self" />
	<link href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/" />
	<id>tag:blog.jmthornton.net,2018-05-02:/</id>
	<updated>2018-05-03T00:00:00Z</updated>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blog.jmthornton.net,2017-10-13:/p/array-removeelement</id>
    <title>Remove an element from an Array in Javascript</title>
    <link href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/array-removeelement" />
  	<updated>2017-10-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>A new Javascript function to remove any element from an Array in an intuitive way, with support for negative indexing</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:blog.jmthornton.net,2018-02-04:/p/xmrstakcompile</id>
    <title>I successfully compiled the xmr-stak miner with CUDA</title>
    <link href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/xmrstakcompile" />
  	<updated>2018-02-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>After many errors and failures, I found a method to successfully compile the xmr-stak unified XMR miner with CUDA support</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:blog.jmthornton.net,2017-10-31:/p/worm-of-1988</id>
    <title>The Internet worm of 1988: A Tour of the Worm</title>
    <link href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/worm-of-1988" />
  	<updated>2017-10-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>On the evening of November 2, 1988, a self-replicating program was released upon the Internet. Within the space of hours this program had spread across the US</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:blog.jmthornton.net,2018-05-03:/p/ecmascript2017</id>
    <title>What's new in ECMAScript 2017</title>
    <link href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/ecmascript2017" />
  	<updated>2018-05-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>Two years ago, ES6 gave a massive update to the already powerful ECMAScript standard. This year's release, ECMAScript 2017, provides several new features and changes. Let's take a look</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:blog.jmthornton.net,2017-09-27:/p/duplicated-ids</id>
    <title>Duplicate IDs in HTML: What would happen?</title>
    <link href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/duplicated-ids" />
  	<updated>2017-09-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>Duplicated IDs occur both intentionally and not, so what happens when a browser tries to render them?</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:blog.jmthornton.net,2017-02-27:/p/thunderbird-ddg</id>
    <title>Set DuckDuckGo as default search in Thunderbird</title>
    <link href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/thunderbird-ddg" />
  	<updated>2017-02-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>For several dwindling reasons, DuckDuckGo can still be tricky to add to some services despite being the default browser for several browsers. A couple years ago, Mozilla broke the old method of adding DuckDuckGo to the settings. They neglected to update their documentation, so here's a little for you</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:blog.jmthornton.net,2016-10-26:/p/protonmail</id>
    <title>Protonmail - Why I switched and you should too</title>
    <link href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/protonmail" />
  	<updated>2016-10-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>ProtonMail is the world’s largest, most user-friendly open source secure email service, developed by CERN and MIT scientists and protected under Swiss privacy law. It brings email privacy back to the people while still maintaining a fantastic user experience characteristic of the first-class email service it is</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:blog.jmthornton.net,2017-03-28:/p/switch-caps-esc</id>
    <title>Switch Caps Lock and Escape (Linux)</title>
    <link href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/switch-caps-esc" />
  	<updated>2017-03-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary>The standard QWERTY keyboard is great in a lot of ways and for a lot of uses. My current keyboard has been with me for years and I know it well, but if I could change the locations of a couple keys, I would. And naturally, that's what I did</summary>
  </entry>

</feed>
