<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US">
  <title>Blog by Jade Michael Thornton</title>
  <link rel="self" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/feed.xml" />
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/" />
	<id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/</id>
	<updated>2024-09-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jade Michael Thornton</name>
  </author>

  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/switch-caps-esc</id>
    <title>Switch Caps Lock and Escape (Linux)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/switch-caps-esc" />
    <published>2016-03-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>The standard QWERTY keyboard is great in a lot of ways and for a lot of uses. My current keyboard has been with me for years and I know it well, but if I could change the locations of a couple keys, I would. And naturally, that's what I did</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/protonmail</id>
    <title>Protonmail - Why I switched and you should too</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/protonmail" />
    <published>2016-10-26T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>ProtonMail is the world’s largest, most user-friendly open source secure email service, developed by CERN and MIT scientists and protected under Swiss privacy law. It brings email privacy back to the people while still maintaining a fantastic user experience characteristic of the first-class email service it is</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/combine-excel</id>
    <title>Combine multiple Excel workbooks into sheets in a single workbook</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/combine-excel" />
    <published>2016-11-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>A quick VBA subroutine for combining multiple Excel workbooks into a single workbook, making ingestion into Tableau easier.</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/thunderbird-ddg</id>
    <title>Set DuckDuckGo as default search in Thunderbird</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/thunderbird-ddg" />
    <published>2017-02-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>For several dwindling reasons, DuckDuckGo can still be tricky to add to some services despite being the default browser for several browsers. A couple years ago, Mozilla broke the old method of adding DuckDuckGo to the settings. They neglected to update their documentation, so here's a little for you</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/duplicated-ids</id>
    <title>Duplicate IDs in HTML: What would happen?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/duplicated-ids" />
    <published>2017-09-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>Duplicated IDs occur both intentionally and not, so what happens when a browser tries to render them?</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/array-removeelement</id>
    <title>Remove an element from an Array in Javascript</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/array-removeelement" />
    <published>2017-10-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>A new Javascript function to remove any element from an Array in an intuitive way, with support for negative indexing</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/xmrstakcompile</id>
    <title>I successfully compiled the xmr-stak miner with CUDA</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/xmrstakcompile" />
    <published>2018-02-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>After many errors and failures, I found a method to successfully compile the xmr-stak unified XMR miner with CUDA support</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/ecmascript2017</id>
    <title>What's new in ECMAScript 2017</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/ecmascript2017" />
    <published>2018-05-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>Two years ago, ES6 gave a massive update to the already powerful ECMAScript standard. This year's release, ECMAScript 2017, provides several new features and changes. Let's take a look</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/clearnightretro</id>
    <title>ClearNight Retro</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/clearnightretro" />
    <published>2018-05-08T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>Introducing a new dark, relaxed retro theme for the Atom text editor</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/tmux-known-socket</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/tmux-known-socket" />
    <title>A Known SSH Socket for Tmux</title>
    <published>2020-05-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>Using a known, shared SSH socket to enable agent forwarding through an existing tmux session</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/jira-commit-msg</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/jira-commit-msg" />
    <title>Automatically add Jira issue to commit message from branch name</title>
    <published>2020-08-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>When your git branch name contains an issue number (e.g. from Jira), automatically format git commit messages with the issue number at the end</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/steam-corrupt-update-files</id>
    <title>Fix Steam 'Corrupt Update Files'</title>
    <published>2020-10-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>How to fix the annoying error when downloading or updating some Steam games, which reports the error 'Corrupt Update Files'</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/git-submodule-deinit</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/git-submodule-deinit" />
    <title>Remove (deinit) a Git submodule</title>
    <published>2020-11-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>A quick reminder of how to remove a Git submodule, because I always forget</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/clean-arch-wumpus</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/clean-arch-wumpus" />
    <title>Halfway on Main: Thoughts on Clean Architecture</title>
    <published>2021-04-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>Uncle Bob ignores his own advice when considering the "Main" component, but we can improve on his thoughts and learn from them</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/emacs-project-override</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/emacs-project-override" />
    <title>Overriding project.el project root in Emacs</title>
    <published>2022-04-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>A short function to override what project.el thinks your project root is with a hidden file</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/fav-lesser-known-packages</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/fav-lesser-known-packages" />
    <title>Some favorite lesser-known Emacs packages</title>
    <published>2023-05-07T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>A few of my favorite lesser-known Emacs packages which don't usually make the top lists</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/snyk-ls-emacs</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/snyk-ls-emacs" />
    <title>Snyk Language Server in Emacs</title>
    <published>2023-06-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>Setting up the Snyk Language Server for use in Emacs by defining a custom server connection in LSP Mode</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/bug-posts</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/bug-posts" />
    <title>A list of the best bug write-ups I've read</title>
    <published>2023-11-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>A modest list of interesting blog posts I've come across containing tech mystery stories exploring how a bug or mistake or other problem came about, how it was discovered, how it was fixed, and maybe some lessons to learn.</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/consult-line-isearch-history</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/consult-line-isearch-history" />
    <title>Connecting consult-line with isearch history</title>
    <published>2024-01-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>Adding the latest consult-line search term to isearch history for easy search continuation</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/org-roam-created-modified-dates</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/org-roam-created-modified-dates" />
    <title>Org-roam: Automatically Set Node Created and Modified Dates</title>
    <published>2024-03-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>Enhancing Org-roam nodes with auto-updating created and modified properties.</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/cave-chains</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jmthornton.net/p/cave-chains" />
    <title>The Chains of Plato's Cave</title>
    <published>2024-09-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <summary>The chains of the prisoners of Plato's allegory of the cave aren't really there holding us down. Critical thinking is one tool which can help us realize the shifting nature of our perceptions.</summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[
        <p>Critical thinking plays a crucial role in adult life, significantly impacting our ability to experience a productive and positive existence.</p>

        <p><a href="http://webspace.ship.edu/cgboer/platoscave.html">Plato's allegory of the cave</a> tells the story of prisoners who have been chained inside a dark cave their entire lives, facing a blank wall. They watch shadows projected on the wall by objects passing in front of a fire behind them, and they believe these shadows are the only reality. One prisoner is freed and exposed to the outside world, discovering that the shadows are just a false representation of reality. When he returns to the cave to enlighten the others, they reject his revelations and cling to their limited view.</p>

        <p>The story is easily seen as an allegory for critical thinking triggered by a traumatic event (the removal from the cave), and the rejection of critical thinking by the remaining prisoners. The abruptly removed prisoner struggles for some time to harmonize his new observations with the assumptions he's lived his entire life, and is forced to conclude that the shadows he knew were not all of reality and indeed not truly things in and of themselves. When he returns to the other prisoners, they show an utter lack of critical thinking and judge him on their own terms rather than considering that their own assumptions could contain flaws.</p>

        <p>Hopefully, the removed prisoner learns continued critical thinking from his experience, and uses his newfound doubt in his assumptions and ways of thinking to drive a curiosity into the way the world truly works. Critical thinking is a process, not an outcome, and the prisoner should enjoy extending the "exploration" phase of their thinking.</p>

        <p>For even greater impact, the newly enlightened prisoner could act as a helper and guide to the others, despite their resistance. In the allegory, he tries to share what he has learned, but they reject him and seem to fear his mad ramblings. They even resolve to put to death anyone who tries to leave the small world they understand. They say this despite their chains which bind them to their positions so tightly that they cannot turn their heads, likely incapable of even seeing each other. With compassion, the freed prisoner could resolve to help them regardless, releasing their chains (perhaps one at a time to mitigate the death threat), and helping each to peer deeper into the world. In our non-hypothetical lives, we are often the prisoners, but our chains are not physical, which can ironically make them harder to remove.</p>

        <p>Yet the shackles that hold us to our assumptions, the beliefs of our parents, the traditions of our cultures, they aren't really there holding us down. Sometimes these chains are more easily released with the help of someone who can show us that our framework of interpreting the world can and should be questioned. By looking inward and recognizing that our perceptions are transient, we open ourselves to limitless potential. Seeing beyond our preconceptions and worldviews, we can begin to understand that our certainties rest on shifting sands. Just as the freed prisoner learned, beliefs that once seemed concrete can dissolve upon careful examination. The approach of critical thinking can help us cultivate a fresh perspective, one that continuously adapts and grows, finding real freedom in questioning and doubting and re-evaluating of our reality.</p>
        ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>

</feed>
